Hey, this is MJ and in today's tutorial,
[music] I'm going to be showing you how
to crochet our timeless granny ripple
blanket.
The yarn that I'm using for the pattern
is my yarn line [music] timeless tones
anti-pilling DK weight yarn in
collaboration with Mary [music] Maxim.
I am using the pinks for this blanket,
[music] but you can choose any five
colors that you want. So, I've chosen
rosewater,
sunset [music] coral, peony pink, petal
pink, and vintage rose.
So, for [music] the blanket, you're
going to need two balls of each color.
>> [music]
[music]
>> The hook that I'll be using for this
pattern is a 5-mm crochet hook, and this
is a metal streamline hook from Furls
Crochet, and we'll link the hook in the
description box below the video.
So, now for the blanket, I've alternated
my colors. So, I've started with the
lighter, I've then gone to the coral,
the peony pink, the petal pink, and then
the vintage rose. Now, I'm going to be
working on a smaller swatch with you,
and I'm going to be working with the
peony pink for the swatch tutorial that
we're going to work through together.
So, our granny ripple pattern is worked
in a multiple of 18. For the blanket,
you're going to chain out 180.
Now, for the smaller swatch, I am just
going to double up our 18 and work
36 chains.
So, I'm going to take a slip knot,
putting it on my crochet hook,
and I'll chain out 36.
>> So now in the fifth chain from the hook,
we're going to work three double
crochet. So 1 2 3
4 5
So there's one
two
and three.
Now we're going to skip the next two
chains and work three double crochet in
the next chain.
So 1 2
and then three double crochet
in the next chain.
Okay, and then we're going to skip
the next two chains.
1 2
And we're going to work
three double crochet.
and then we're going to chain two
and work three double crochet in the
same space.
Okay, so you can see we've made a peak
by doing the increase in that one chain.
So now we're going to
skip the next two chains.
1 2
and work three double crochet in the
next.
And we're going to do that twice.
So, there's our three doubles. Skip the
next two chains, 1, 2, and in the next
we'll do three doubles.
And then we're going to skip five chains
for our valley. So, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
And in the next
chain, we're going to work three double
crochet.
We're going to skip two chains, 1, 2,
and work three double crochet in the
next.
Now, we're going to skip two, 1, 2, and
in the next chain we're going to work
three double crochet.
Chain two and three double crochet.
Okay, we're going to skip the next two
chains, three double crochet.
Skip two chains and three double
crochet.
Okay, and then as you work across your
blanket, you would be coming to another
valley.
So, let's just take a look before we
end.
We're going up with three clusters,
chain two,
down with three clusters,
then we have our valley,
going up with three, our chain two,
going down with three, and then you
would have another valley, and you're
just going to continue across your
blanket in this manner. But, now what
we're going to do
is we're going to end in the final chain
with a double crochet. So, when you get
to the end of your blanket,
you'll be ending a double crochet in the
last.
And now if you count your clusters
across the entire blanket, you're going
to have 60 clusters.
We have 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12.
So, that will complete our foundation
row, and now we're going to work row
one, and we'll start with a chain four.
1 2 3
4, and this counts as a double crochet.
And then we're going to do three double
crochets between
our clusters.
So, right in the space between
one,
two,
three, and we're going to do that twice,
so we're going to do it again here.
Okay, and then in our chain two space,
we're going to work three double
crochet.
A chain two.
And three double crochet.
Okay, so we've
done our peak right here.
And then we're going to work our three
DC clusters between our groups. So,
three double crochet between these two
clusters.
One.
Two.
Three.
And between the next.
One.
Two.
Three.
And now here's our valley. We're going
to skip
this space right here,
which will help pull it to give it that
point. And we're going to go across and
we'll do our three clusters
between the next two spaces.
And this one.
Okay, and then we're back to our chain
two space at the top. So, we'll work
three double crochet.
Chain two
and three double crochet all in that
same space.
Okay, and then we're going to come back
down putting our three DC clusters in
our spaces between.
So, one
two
three
one
two
three
Okay, and then we're coming to the end
and we're going to finish off with a
double crochet in that turning chain.
And now for the pattern, we're just
going to be repeating this row, but
we'll work through it again together one
more time.
So, just like before, we started with a
chain four.
We turn.
And then we're going to work our three
DC clusters between these next two
spaces.
So, one
two
three
one
two
three
And then in our chain two space, we're
going to do three double crochet.
Chain two and three double crochet.
Okay, and then we're going to do
a cluster between here, a cluster
between here, and then when we get to
the valley, we skip the space and then
work up to the next two.
Three DC cluster.
Next space.
One.
Two.
Three.
Skip the valley space.
And then we're going back up. One.
Two.
Three.
And in the next
one.
Two.
Three.
And then our chain two space.
One.
Two.
Three. Chain two.
One.
Two.
Three.
And then we'll work back down clusters
in between.
So you can see what a quick and easy
pattern this is. Very easy to memorize.
And it's going to work up really quick.
And in that turning chain we'll work a
double crochet to finish it off.
Okay, and this is going to keep our
sides
nice and straight
as we go.
And now when we look at our color
pattern,
we're changing colors. We're going to
work our foundation row plus rows 1
through 13
in our first color, which is going to be
about 10 in worth of color.
Then we're going to change over to color
B
and we're going to work
14 rows. So each color we're going to do
14 rows. Now if you want to alter the
size of the blanket, you can do so, but
based on the pattern and the yarn that
we've used, we're doing 14 rows of each
color.
Okay, so I just want to show you how to
change your color.
So you're going to be changing color
always on the right side
or at the end of the wrong side of your
work. So we're going to end off with a
double crochet
and I like to yarn over with the new
color on the last yarn over, so we'll
pull through.
And then we'll go ahead and chain four.
Okay, and then you'll have these tails
to weave in, but you're now just going
to continue and the new color will begin
on the right side of your work.
And I'm just doing this as a
demonstration, but you'll have worked
your 14
rows.
Okay, and then you can just go ahead
working with the next color, you can cut
the first color and continue.
And what I find is a helpful little tip
when working this pattern is you're
always going to have three clusters
going up, three clusters going down,
three clusters going up, three clusters
going down. And that will help you keep
track to make sure you stay on track
with your clusters as you work across.
So now here's a bit bigger swatch I was
working on and I'm going to show you how
to do the edge.
Okay, so we're finishing on our wrong
side
and for the blanket you'll be finishing
at row 69.
We'll then chain one.
Okay, so then we're working back across
now the right side.
We're going to single crochet in the
first stitch,
chain two,
and single crochet
all in that same stitch.
We'll skip the next stitch, single
crochet,
chain two,
single crochet.
Skip the next stitch, single crochet,
chain two, single crochet.
And we're going to keep doing this all
the way way across. So skipping a stitch
and then single, chain two, single
all in the same
space. And we're going to end
[clears throat] up with this beautiful
little
picot
edging across the blanket.
And here I'm coming to the chain two, so
I'll just go ahead
and do the same thing in the chain two.
>> Okay, and
I'm just finishing off in the last
stitch here.
Okay, so you're just going to work it
like this all the way across the top,
and then we can fasten off. I'm not
going to do anything along the sides of
the blanket. We're just leaving them
like this.
Okay, so we can fasten that off, and
then we're also going to join back.
So, we're going to go to the wrong side.
We're going to go across this in single
crochet to start with, and then we will
do our picot edge across here, as well.
So, we're getting our two chains
between.
Oops.
And then a single crochet.
And just working this across.
>> Okay, so once you work evenly across, I
started with one.
Working my stitches across.
And [clears throat] then we're going to
chain one and turn at the end.
And now we're we're back to the right
side and we'll do the same. So we'll
single crochet,
chain two,
skip the next,
single,
chain two,
single in the same stitch.
Okay, so once you finish getting across,
you can just fasten off and then you can
weave in all of your tails.
That wraps up today's [music] tutorial.
I hope you enjoyed the video. Make sure
to check the description box below for
[music] the yarn and pattern links.
Thanks so much guys. Have an awesome
day.
>> [music]